[Music]
Heat.
Hello everybody. Good day and good
evening to all of you wherever you are
in the world and welcome to episode 271
of the Askabil show. I hope everybody is
doing great and today I'm going to take
questions that you all have asked in the
comments. I've chosen about 20 or so
questions um and I'm going to take those
and I saw that a bunch of questions came
in in the past 1 hour but I was not able
to take those. So in the future if you
want to ask questions please ask them
like you know an hour or two before the
show starts because at the last minute I
can't really pick and choose questions
select questions. Uh with that said
let's see who all is there on the live
chat. I can say Vamshi Kalem anonymous
scientist chat DSP Sujit Shaagandha the
civilizational warrior Vidan Singh
Jagish Mali Barat first Anand Pai uh who
else we have Blitzkrieg chat PS DSP
again Vidash Dalmutra Kapil Shrimp
Hunter Canve Shivasai Amisha Mishra Mr.
Saka Duvya Aayush Singh Vimla Chodri U
Shubhham Sik Shriyan GK U Geopolitical
Di from Indor Krishna Gunar from the
Surinamese Netherlands
uh Shou Agarwal Panipal from Kolkata
Rashmi Rat from Rajasthan Shri Ran
Chandra Namaha Jiram Rahul Dunak
Navin Kumar Kub Bhagwat Omar Nilab
engineer Naven Kumar wooden armor PK
Deep Patel from Australia 12:30 in the
night in Australia Bad Deep Patel is
watching. Thank you so much for being on
the live chat sir. Uh Himman Shukla, Abi
Abishek, Vidant, Eclipse Files, Hari,
Chan, Gokul, Mlab, Jesam, uh J Alan, J
Victor, who else we have? Rutij, Aush
Si, uh Reina, Tari, Ankita, hello, the
civilizational warrior, Jirroj Kamat, uh
Varun, Reddi, and so many other people.
Master Diddy's something or the other.
uh Eclipse files
and everybody else. So uh thank you so
much for being on on on the show. I
really appreciate that. And with that
said, I think we should start taking
some questions. Just give me a second. I
need to pull something up so that we can
um where do we have it? Right here we
have it. Okay. So let's get going with
the questions.
What's the first question that we have
for today? And it's going to be
interesting questions. We're going to
start with this. Uh so we have Sur and
Adita Gag. Uh okay. Thank you so much
Suresh. Uh the question is recently
released recording of Ahmedabad flight
accident. It has a conversation where
they say that the line of fuel or
something was cut off where both day uh
they didn't etc. Is there a possibility
of sabotage behind this? your analogy of
analogy uh flight experienced flight
pilots one experienced another also
somewhat experienced no conclusion in
the report they say possibility of
sabotage uh some say pilot mistake I
think sabotage what what's my opinion is
what you want to know and should Boeing
be saved despite the questions raised on
the standards of the aircraft they
manufacture and possible manufacturing
defects that could have caused the crash
in Gujarat uh as the global aero
economic depends on the trust shown on
Boeing and if that collapses it might
create the global chaos is that the
reason the reports were first
intentionally leaked to the US first
yeah and official statements were made
in India after that okay all kinds of
questions obviously everybody is very
concerned about what's happening uh this
report has come out recently right the
AIB report has come out the AIB is an
Indian government organization the
aircraft accident investigation bureau
right it's a division of the ministry of
uh civil aviation government of India
and its job is to investigate aircraft
accidents and incidents in India. Now
this AIB has come up with this report
and the report raises more questions and
answers and the report seems to
deliberately
you know give information that is
unimportant and it seems to skip
information that is crucial to our
understanding of what happened. It's
telling you what time at what second the
plane started taxiing towards the runway
and what second it did something or the
other. But the crucial evidence as to
when the engines were cut off, at
exactly what time did the aircraft start
rolling, rotating, what time did the
wheels take off from the ground, at what
time did the actual uh engine cut off
happened, what time were the switches
flipped or whatever, you know, the fuel
fuel switches flipped. Uh what was the
maximum altitude that the that the
aircraft achieved? What was the maximum
speed the aircraft achieved? The entire
second by-c chronology is not given.
They have not released a transcript or a
recording of the conversation between
the pilots. They're putting selective
selected you know cherrypicked things
here and there possibly out of context.
There is no signature on the uh AIB
report preliminary report. There are
tremendous inconsistencies and red flags
in the report this preliminary report.
And uh you know I am not a pilot but our
friend Gorov Tanja flying beast is a
pilot and he's put out an excellent
series of three videos on his channel. I
would highly re recommend you watch this
those three videos in which he has
completely
totally shown the how how bad this
report is and how many questions it
raises and he says that he has no he
doesn't have any you know confidence in
the AIB and obviously if they don't put
a put signatures on the report and they
release the report in the middle of the
night like 2:00 a.m. 3:00 a.m. or 1:00
a.m. whatever time it was India time and
if they leak the report 24 hours before
releasing it in India to the to the Wall
Street Journal there are lots of
questions that are going to be raised
right it looks like the engines failed
immediately
at the point of takeoff
not when you when the aircraft starts
rotating which means the nose lifts up
but it looks like the engines failed
immediately when the the the wheels left
the ground or maybe a second after that.
And there is a clear procedure when dual
engine failure happens that you take the
fuel switches, you cut them off, then
you put them on. And that's what the
pilots did.
And that happens only a few seconds
after the the uh dual engine failure
happens. And immediately when the when
the jet engines fail, the aircraft
doesn't lose power immediately because
of inertia. It will keep rising for a
while and the speed will actually
increase for a while. It's only after
that is done when that that momentum is
dissipated that the aircraft starts
going down. So there are tremendous
questions. There are huge red flags in
this AIB report and uh you know Boeing
has Boeing used to have the greatest
safety record track record of of all the
aircraft manufacturers
but there have been lots of problems
with Boeing in the recent past and they
have been caught red-handed trying to
you know cover up things. There's this
system that they had on the Boeing 737
Max, this MCCast system that was faulty
and they did not even tell the world and
the pilots of the world that this system
was installed on the aircraft and the
system would try and hijack the aircraft
when when the when the angle of attack
sensors would be defective and it'll try
and pitch the nose down 10 seconds down
and then the pilots will try and pull it
off for 5 seconds and again the uh the
the computer will take out and start
pitching the nose down for for 10
seconds and eventually it leads to
crashes. So there was a Lion Air crash
in Indonesia I think 2018 or 2019 and a
few months later there was a Ethiopian
uh aircraft that crashed because of that
crashed because of this this system that
Boeing tried to hide. It's a completely
new system they had installed on the
aircraft Boeing 737 Max aircraft
and they did not and and if you install
a new system like that you have to have
the pilots trained on that but Boeing
did not even tell any airline
that this new system is there and even
after they realized that it caused the
first crash they still did not take any
action and then second crash happened.
First, Indonesia out of Jakarta.
Secondly, Ethiopia out of Adis Ababa,
lots of problems.
So, Boeing has these issues. Their
quality standards have dropped
drastically in the in the recent years.
Uh, and they are known to hide such
things. And when the first crash
happened, the Lion Air crash out of
Jakarta, they tried to blame the pilot.
The pilots, there was an Indian pilot
who was flying the aircraft. Obviously
you have two pilots right in in an
aircraft. One of them was Indian. They
tried to lay the blame on the pilots.
Even when the second aircraft crashed,
the the Ethiopian one, they again tried
to tried to blame the pilots despite
knowing full well that they were
entirely responsible for this. So I you
know I think uh the government of India
the prime minister's office needs to
look into this uh this this uh
investigation this preliminary
investigation report that's been
released by the AI AIB aircraft accident
investigation bureau uh we cannot trust
it. They have not even bothered to put
this you know the the the AIB heads
signature on the report. a report
without any signatures. It means they're
trying to cover them their backsides
because they know that this is there
there is something super wrong with the
report.
So I think this needs to be looked into
by the at the highest level but this is
a international incident accident. This
is a this is a question of India's
safety record. It's a question of the
safety of of passengers who fly every
day. Thousands of flights right and
hundreds of thousands of people probably
fly every day. This is a very sensitive
matter and and who is it that that's on
the board of the AIB? Each of those
individuals needs needs to be
investigated.
Who is the person or who are the persons
who leaked the report to the to the Wall
Street Journal 24 hours before it was
released in the middle of the night in
India. Who are those people? They are
government of India officials. There are
tremendous problems. Ive I've I've said
this right? I've said this so many
times. At the root of every problem in
India is corruption.
So uh
I don't know see I can't tell what the
what the cause of the crash is but it's
clearly a dual engine failure that
happened at the moment of liftoff or
just after liftoff like a second or two
after liftoff.
That's what happened. But what caused
the dual engine failure? That's the big
mystery.
That is the big mystery
and I don't have the answer right now.
That's what the government needs to look
into. You have the the the two
recorders, right? The voice recorder and
the data recorder. They will have all
the answers.
Those need to be investigated
by professionals, by competent
authorities, not by I don't know people
who apparently may be compromised.
That's what needs to happen. Huge
problem here. Huge problem.
Um I don't believe for one microscond
for one for for one nancond that the
pilots are responsible for what
happened. I don't think the pilots
caused
this crash. I think they tried their
best to fight to to ensure the the you
know to to make to save the aircraft as
as as much as possible until the very
end. That's what it looks like.
Uh but as usual they'll try and blame
the the pilots. the pilots aren't here
to defend themselves. You know, they
died. Uh, and uh, so I am not going to
at this point in time point fingers at
at maybe an aircraft manufacturer, maybe
a nation or whatever. My question is who
the I mean what the what happened with
the AIB report. They did not even have
the courage to put their signatures on
the report.
Huge problem there. You need we need to
start the investigation with the with
the people who who wrote that report
with the people with the person or
persons who leaked the report to the
west to the Wall Street Journal and the
Wall Street Journal seems to know
everything more than what the government
of India knows right now as if they have
the full recording of of the of the
conversation it looks like how did they
get their hands on all of this and and
if the Wall Street Journal has it why
isn't it being released by the
government of India to the people of
India the entire recording the not the
not the transcript, the recording
itself, the audio recording.
There are huge red flags here. So, I uh
I don't know if it's sabotage or
whatever. I know there's all kinds of
speculation. What I am clear about is
that this is like almost certain to be a
dual engine failure that happened at the
point of liftoff or maybe just a second
or so after liftoff after the wheels
left the ground. and the the fuel
switches were set to cut and then back
to on as part of the procedure that
you're supposed to do when there's a
dual engine failure. So that's what the
pilots did later a few seconds after the
dual engine failure happened. Uh so
that's what I can say at this time.
Boeing obviously will want this to be
categorized as pilot error. The United
States will want this to be categorized
as pilot error. The question is why is
the AIB aiding them in this?
Uh so the government of India is very
quiet right now and it looks like the
full investigation report may take a
year or so. I don't know. But if there
is a problem with Boeing aircraft in the
meanwhile,
I mean are we going to wait one year
until the report comes out? What if
there are more such incidents in the
meanwhile? Do we want more people to
die?
So that's the deal. I I don't have the
answer right now. But I am 100% crystal
clear about the fact that the pilots did
not do this deliberately. They fought
until the end to save the aircraft. They
had the training kick in. They did
everything as per the training and as
per the the manual and as per the memory
items. That's what they did.
And to blame the pilots say you're
trying to save somebody. So who is it
that you're trying to save? AIB. That's
the question. So that's what I have to
say at this point in time. I don't have
the answers. the answers are buried deep
in the data that's part of the data
recorder that that was recorded in the
data recorder in the in the cockpit
voice recorder those need to be
investigated and please don't leak those
to the Wall Street Journal or whoever so
there are big question there are many
more questions that actually uh you know
need to be answered so uh yeah it's it's
a mystery right now and clearly there
seems to be some kind of cover up going
on right our own people are they seem to
be part of the cover up. So I think the
prime minister's office need to needs to
look into this personally and get to the
bottom of the matter as soon as
possible. Don't please don't wait for a
year. Okay? There could be more lives at
stake. Everyday people are flying on
Boeing aircraft in in the country all
across the world. Innocent people,
completely innocent people. We don't
want more lives to be lost. Boeing has
the has a track record when it comes to
the 737 Max of uh trying to suppress
what they knew was a fatal flaw in the
aircraft.
Uh and and you know was this sabotage? I
don't know. I I I don't know at this
point in time. Uh we have discussed kill
switches in the past in the context of
military aircraft, haven't we?
We have discussed that. What's a kill
switch? A kill switch is uh something
that can be remotely activated by the
original equipment manufacturer
remotely. So maybe the equipment was
manufactured on the other side of the
planet and it's been sold to country X.
Okay. And maybe under certain conditions
the manufacturer doesn't want country X
to be able to uh operate the equipment.
So maybe they can remotely disable the
equipment. That's called a kill switch
and such things. This is not science
fiction. This is very feasible. We have
discussed examples of this in the past,
haven't we? The FA18 fighter planes that
the Americans sold to the Australians in
the 1980s. What happened to those?
What happened? Those the Australians
were not able to use them. They were not
able to uh lock the target acquisition
systems onto targets of their choice.
And this persisted for like more than
two decades until they were able to
crack the system.
Israel had sold some weapons systems to
Azarbaijan
and a few years ago during a period of
tensions between Israel and Azarbaijan.
The weapon systems mysteriously failed
to failed to work.
Right? This is nothing new. Kill
switches. You can remotely disable
equipment.
So is it possible that you could have
kill switches in commercial civilian
aircraft? If you can have them in
military aircraft, why can't you have
them in commercial aircraft?
I mean this MCAST system, that's an
example of a kill switch.
That's an example you could say of a
kill switch. If the angle of attack
sensor is disabled for some reason or or
it you you make it transmit faulty
information to the computer, MCAST kicks
in and kills the aircraft. So, you know,
there's a lot of possibilities out
there. But right now, we don't have the
answers. So, my point is that this this
report that has been put out by AIB that
raises huge red flags. The entire
personnel of the AIB needs to be
investigated
and uh the report needs to be looked
into. What are they trying to hide and
who are they trying to help? That's what
I would say. Okay.
Right. Uh WRV says why is it that some
countries have accepted very unfair
trade deals like with the US like
Indonesia recently did a trade deal with
the US where they have to remove all
tariffs while the US gets to keep 19%
and Indonesia has pledged to purchase
$15 billion worth of US energy $4.5
billion in agricultural products 50
Boeing jets 50 boeing okay not airbing
jets wonderful many of them the long
hole 777 models. Why didn't Indonesia
accept a US trade pack with non
reciprocal unilateral market access in
exchange for a 19% tariff gap despite
the significant economic and political
trade-offs and what strategic policy
framework should India adopt to avoid
similar dependencies while strengthening
its negotiating position? So I looked
into this uh I have this report here
okay an overview of the recent US
Indonesia trade deal. Incredible. What
are the key terms of the agreement? Key
terms. Let's let's say the key terms. Um
tariffs on Ind Indonesian exports. The
US has agreed to lower very kindly, very
magnanimously, the US has agreed to
lower its proposed tariff on Indonesian
goods from 32% to a uniform 19%. Okay,
very kind, very magnanimous of the US.
And this is the reduction from the
earlier threat. It is still
significantly higher than the previous
average of about 5% that was applied
that applied in 2024.
Okay. Now access for US exports,
American goods with very minor
exceptions like alcoholic beverages and
pork will enter Indonesia tariff-free.
No tariffs on American goods except for
alcoholic stuff and and pork which
Indonesians don't like. Additionally, US
products are exempt from Indonesia's
local content rules and certain import
quotas. So blanket exemption for US
exports except for pork and alcohol.
Well, yeah. Now, what about purchases by
Indonesia in exchange for this
magnanimous reduction, okay, from 32 to
19%. Indonesia has committed to buying
about $15 billion in energy, American
energy exports, oil, natural gas, etc.,
etc. Indonesia's committed to purchasing
uh $4.5 billion in US agricultural goods
including GMOs, GMO products, multi-year
commitment for wheat and other staples.
Indonesia has also committed to buying
50 Boeing aircraft for its national
airline Guda Garuda Airlines. Right. Uh
trade compliance. Indonesia has agreed
to enforce measures to prevent US-bound
goods being rerouted or transcripped
from third countries especially China.
Um this makes Indonesia the Assean
country with the lowest U US tariff
under US recent recent US trade actions
uh and so on. So tremendous tariff
asymmetry.
Yeah. US goods receive almost full
access to the Indonesian market without
any tariffs. almost no tariffs, but
Indonesian exports to the US will be
subject to a substantial 19% tariff,
four times higher than the previous
average.
It puts Indonesian exporters at a
tremendous disadvantage,
right? And Indonesia is is compelled to
buy these huge specific purchases of US
goods, energy, agriculture, aircraft,
about 20 billion in total, maybe more.
And uh how did this agreement come
about? So the agreement came from the US
threatening extremely high tariffs. Uh
it's like that gun to the head. Take it
or leave it. Yeah. you either accept 19%
or we will put 500 or thousand% or god
knows what. This is called gun to the
head diplomacy. Right? So that's what
the Americans have done to Indonesia and
the Indonesian government is saying it's
the best possible outcome because you
know they alternative was was was
you know something you can't imagine um
and so on. So this is this is like
Indonesia has been made to capitulate by
the by the Americans.
Uh that's the deal.
So that's what happens when you are the
superpower. You can put a gun to
someone's head and make them accept
whatever you want. And then you said
that you know magna I will magnanimously
bring the tariffs down from 32% like I
had promised earlier to only 19%. But
you cannot you know impose any tariffs
any substantial significant tariffs on
my goods. What kind of policies are
these? These are East India Company
policies.
The US is going to bear Indonesia and
it's going to bear everybody else. Turn
everybody into beggars. That's what
they're trying to do. That's what they
intend to do. And uh well, if you are
Indonesia, if you are a smaller, weaker
country, what is it that you can do
about it?
The the choice is either 19% or 3,000%.
What you going to do? And then you to
purchase uh agricultural products and
energy exports and and 50 aircraft. It's
like paying tribute. It's like a vasal
paying tribute to his overlord.
It's like Judea paying tribute to Rome.
It's like sis alpine or transalpine go
paying tribute to Rome. every year you
have to go and give them x amount of
gold and y amount of whatever else and
these many numbers of slaves
and much more. This is the same tribute
system. The US is an empire, my friends.
And now they're behaving like an empire.
It's no longer subtle and and
sophisticated. Now it's out in the open.
So that is the deal. I'm I'm feel sorry
for Indonesia, but such is the world. I
mean the world has always always
operated this way. the past 70 years or
80 years was this was an aberration a
period of and yeah it was an aberration.
Now we are back to standard imperial
tactics. So uh the question now is what
strategic policy framework should India
adopt to avoid similar situation and
strengthening its negotiating position.
Well, one of the leverages we have is
that u
um we are the only nation in Asia that
is willing to stand up to China and can
act as a genuine counterbalance to
China. Right? That's one leverage we
have and the US needs India when it
comes to uh counterbalance in China.
India is a critical component of India
of the US's uh so-called Indopacific
strategy. India is a member of the Quad
and much more right. Um and we also have
the option of if required if the
Americans push us too far we can even
somehow find it you know come to a deal
with China possibly who knows so we have
uh options we have leverage uh the
Americans have also well it's not like
they don't have leverage they are
currently threatening 500% tariffs on
India
right Lindsey Graham's uh bill which is
getting tremendous bipartisan support
anyone who trades with Russia and
purchases Russian oil is is could
potentially be subject to 500% tariffs.
So that's a threat that's dangling over
overhead. Trump is also threatening
that, right? Uh and they want us to
accept their third rate agricultural
exports, genetically modified organisms
and
you know ghastly stuff. All the stuff
that makes Americans sick. It riddles
Americans with cancer and obesity and
diabetes and whatnot. They want to
export it to us. The government is
saying no. And that's why the trade deal
did not happen by the July 9 deadline.
Now it's August 1 or something. We'll
see about that. Yeah.
Uh so we are not in the same position as
Indonesia but we are in a similar
position.
Uh there are certain differences between
India and Indonesia obviously I don't
think I will explain that. Um so it's
it's terrible what what the Americans
have done to to Indonesia. These are
East India Company tactics. Absolutely.
This is exactly how the East India
Company destroyed India. India's
economy. India was the world's first
fully industrialized civilization. You
are not taught this in your school in
your in your history books. We were a
fully industrialized society.
The British destroyed that. How did they
destroy it? By uh by using the same
tactics. U they opened up the Indian
economy to extremely cheap exports of
third rate material from the UK textiles
and whatnot. and they imposed extremely
high tariffs on Indian exports which
made Indian exports unviable and it
destroyed India's industries and they
also used a whole different range of
tactics. So they completely
de-industrialized India. They poorized
beggarized India. On top of that they
imposed hundreds of artificial famines
and so on. So uh this is you know same
tactics we are seeing over here and
we're going to see much more of that.
This is just the beginning of the uh
American trade war on the world. They're
trying to destroy the entire system they
have themselves built.
Well, there you have it.
Okay. Danush says is the in the current
climate in the west with all their
Russia secondary sanctions threats and
increased pressure on India they're
putting regarding the
India Russia relationship. Do you think
it's actually feasible for India to
actually purchase the Sukoy 57 in this
current geopolitical climate? And if
not, what options does India really
have? Because the F-35 is obviously a no
no and AMCA will take time. Can India
still handle Pakistan in this case?
Right? So we have this current
geopolitical climate. The US is saying
that anybody who trades with Russia will
get these secondary sanctions and
anybody who buys Russian oil will get
500% tariffs and whatnot. Yeah. All that
stuff. and they are obviously singling
out India often uh and sending this
message to India that you know we will
destroy destroy your economy if you deal
with Russia. So then the question is the
we know that the Russians have offered
the Suka 57 with apparently complete
transfer of technology to India and
local manufacturing to India. I think
it's a great deal. Uh some genius
experts are saying this the F-35 is
better. The F-35 is a better aircraft
and the Suka 57 stealth characteristics
aren't that great. Who cares? It's a
fifth generation fighter plane. Even if
it is just okay out of 100, if it gets a
score of even 4550, it's still a fifth
generation fighter plane. And we can
absorb the technology and make it better
iterative iteratively. It's better than
having nothing,
right? The AMCA will will roll out in
what 2030 31 you will have the first
quadrants, you know, by 2035 or
something. You want to wait 10 years for
that to happen? No. And the F-35 is
absolutely no. No. The day we purchased
the F-35, I will announce officially
that we are now a US Vasal. Okay. The
F-35 is a no no. It's a flying trash
can. Terrible aircraft. Extremely
expensive and riddled with kill switches
and back doors.
The moment you purchase that, you are
officially a vasal of the US. You have
lost your sovereignty.
F-35 is a no no. It's a no-go for us.
The AMC will take time. Suko 57, the
Americans could impose crushing
sanctions on India if we purchase that.
The Russians would like us to buy it and
they are apparently offering full
technology transfer local production and
integration with the with the Sukoy 35
MKI ecosystem. So, it'll be very easy
for India to start producing and using
the F Sukoy 57. It's actually a good
deal in my opinion.
So what options does India have? What
options do we have? Well, let's say we
can't we obviously can't buy the F F-35.
Garbage AMCA another 10 years. We can't
wait for that. So 57 too much American
pressure. We can't buy it. So what do we
do? What do we do? Have you heard of the
Safh deal? I'm I'm I'm hearing that
India and France have finalized a deal
about the Safong engines uh which will
um possibly there will be full
technology transfer to India at a very
high price obviously like I've been
saying buy big borrow steel whatever the
price buy it so it looks like that deal
is being now being done so we will
acquire Safh's jet engine technology and
and jointly co-develop a 120 kon engine
in the next few years now as long as
this is a genuine deal and it happens
happens and it doesn't take 10 years to
finalize like it often does with India
you know everything takes years and
years of negotiating and all get it done
fast and start producing the the engines
in the next 5 years I think that's great
if you can do that if that deal goes
ahead and if it is a done deal and if it
actually proceeds then I think we should
just go ahead with the Rafal the Rafal
isn't a bad aircraft it's a 4.5
generation fighter plane I think and we
know how to operate it we we have very
highly trained pilots pilots who have
been operating it for quite a while the
Rafal. So I think if the Suko 57 we
can't get it, we can't accept it because
of American too much American pressure
and we obviously can't get the F-35 then
the option is the HFAL get 1004 one
whatever number of Rafal we need is a
stop gap stop gap measure until we have
the AMCA that's what I would say is the
option that we have it's not a bad
aircraft it's obviously not a fifth
generation aircraft but it's not I mean
it's better than nothing to get a bunch
Profiles. Yeah, that could be the uh
stop gap solution.
And with that we come to the question of
the Safhan engine. Nimish and Sergeant
Skylon. India will be going with the
French engine with full technology
transfer in intellectual property. Does
this mean we can start manufacturing
these locally? India finally closed a
deal for the co-development of a jet
engine with Francis Safh for our AMC
project with full technology transfer
with for about 7 billion USD. What other
critical military technologies should we
focus on acquiring, co-developing,
innovating next that would put India at
the pinnacle of modern warfare? Look,
forget about the pinnacle of modern
warfare. We need a jet engine. That's a
crucial critical uh piece of the puzzle.
Once we have that, we're going to be in
good shape, right? Then we can develop
any kind of aircraft we want and put the
jet engines on that.
Forget about the pinnacle. We'll forget
about flying. Let's first learn how to
run. you know we we have we have learned
how to walk now we will learn how to jog
then then sprint then perhaps fly in the
future so pinnacle of modern warfare
we'll think of it later uh so I think
the c critical military technology we
need is obviously a fifth generation
fighter plane and and a jet engine even
more than the fifth generation fighter
plane it's the jet engine that we need
once we can manufacture that at home as
many as we need as and when we need and
that's it then we can develop any kind
of aircraft we for and we are not
dependent on somebody from outside on
some external actor and we are no longer
hostage to an external actor or actors
as is as has been the case throughout
our history. So one hears that this uh
is going ahead we are going to pay 7
billion USD there's going to be
co-development of a jet engine with
Safhan and I don't know how long it
takes hopefully we should be able So
what does it mean? It means that we're
going to start we're going to
manufacture these locally in India.
There's going to be full technology
transfer and the intellectual property
will be ours as well as the French.
It'll be jointly owned. But we can do
whatever with we want with it and we can
even take in other different directions
and we can have create derivative
engines. We can improve the engine
whatever it's up to us. But once we have
a fully functional jet engine 120 kon
newtons that is as good as anything the
French have. Well, that is a huge relief
for us, right? Which we can produce
ourselves without having to import spare
parts from somewhere else. So, I think
that's the deal. So, I would
hope that this becomes operationalized
as full as poss as soon as possible and
then the next 3 to 5 years we start
manufacturing.
If the negotiations go on for the next 3
to 5 years, then it's a joke. Okay?
We've had enough of this nonsense. All
talk talk talk going on forever. Yep. So
the the manufacturing needs to start in
the next 3 to 5 years. That's that's the
deal. That's that's what I'm hoping for.
If that does happen, well that's a huge
problem solved for India. Yeah. Uh so so
I think if this is indeed true what's
being reported then it is extremely
welcome news. Now, let's see if the
Americans apply any pressure on the
French because the Americans are known
to backstab the French from time to
time. The French recently had this deal
with the Australians, the AUK US. No,
not the AUK US deal, the the the uh the
Scorpain submarine deal. Though the
French were supposed to sell to the
Australians a bunch of Scorpion
submarines and this this deal was
signed. It was proceeding and then the
Americans armed twisted the Australians
and the Australians said sorry France we
are walking off out of the deal
unilaterally
and then the Australians went ahead with
the Americans and they have this AUK US
deal now right nuclear submarines
extremely expensive nuclear submarines
that the Australians will buy from the
Americans and that will not really be
owned by Australia they'll still be
owned by the Americans more or less de
facto so uh so there's always the danger
of that that the Americans has become an
arm twist the French but hopefully it
doesn't happen and then it is great news
for us. So I think it's it's great news
um um that's this is being reported by
the Indian media right now. I hope it is
true. I hope we go ahead with this and I
hope we operationalize this as soon as
possible and I hope we start producing
these engines within the next 3 to 5
years. That would be a huge problem
solved for India and you know then yeah
nations then nations like the US will
have way less leverage over us. Right
now the Americans I mean we have we have
this deal with the Americans for those
uh F404 or whatever engines for over
ages fighter planes. We have paid the
money and all that but they are not
delivering it. Now this year they're
going to deliver like now finally they
have delivered one or two jet engines
and by the end of this year they'll
deliver another another 10 or 12. It's
peanuts.
It's peanuts. They're making India
suffer like this despite us having
signed the deal agreement and having
paid for the jet engines. So that's what
you can do. That's the kind of leverage
the Americans have. Once we start
manufacturing our own jet engines
co-developed with France, then the
Americans will have zero leverage over
us in the matter of jet engines. And
that's what we need to achieve as soon
as possible. So I think it's great news.
It's a great development.
Sahil Patel says what does S Patel say?
Uh well thank you first of all. Thank
you very much. Aruna Shikim Bhutanachi
not equivalent to area of Tibet in
square kilometers. Okay. Why? All right.
Fine. Hasn't India escalated the matter
of Tibet being independent too far? Why?
Why?
Why? Why is it why has it gone too far?
Why? And what does that have to do with
the size and shape and and land area of
Arunachal Pradesh, Tekkim, Bhutan,
Nakai? It has nothing to do nothing to
do with that. What we are doing is the
right thing. We are ramping up the
pressure on China in a very calibrated
manner. It's symbolic pressure on China.
They're not crossing any military red
lines but this is this is these are
diplomatic uh tactics and strategies and
uh the Chinese themselves have you know
caused this through their actions right
uh they have come out openly in support
of Pakistan they they are now not hiding
it that they consider Pakistan to be a
strategic asset for the for China
against India and they will arm Pakistan
as as much as possible and they were
apparently sharing information in real
time with Pakistan at the time of
operation Synindur. So these are
extremely hostile uh actions against
India. Uh China is harboring uh
anti-India terrorists on their soil.
They have this guy the head of Ulfa
right Pares Barua who resides in Yunan
which is part of China
occupied Yunan right. So they harbor
anti-India terrorists. They do all kinds
of things that hurt India's interests.
Um they aid Pakistan. You got to do you
got to give it back to them right to
China. So we are now putting Tibet in
the gray zone. Tibet essentially is now
a disputed territory. That's what we are
saying. And recently Dr. Jashunker
visited Beijing as part of the SEO thing
and he met with Mr. Xiinping after a
bunch after I don't know a long time.
And let's see where it goes. Is there a
kind of they thought again threatening
to happen? I mean last year the Chinese
were saying that you know we want better
relations with India and they we you
know reduce the number of troops on both
sides of the LAC India Tibet LAC last
year uh for the first time after the
Galwan incident and all. Um but the
Chinese have been ramping up their
infrastructure building activities on
the on their side of the LAC. So it's
not like they are you know uh trying to
diffuse the tensions they're eating
Pakistan
they're harboring anti-india terrorists
they're doing so all these things so
obviously India has to respond in some
kind it's not like we don't have any
leverage we have leverage we have
tremendous leverage
the Tibetan government in exile
is is in India the largest Tibetan
diaspora is in India the highest ranking
Buddhist spiritual leader in the world
the Dalai Lama is a resident of India
and so and so on so forth right so we
are not we have not escalated the matter
of Tibet being independent of whatever
true are absolutely not we have not even
started we need to go further it all
depends on on how China on what China's
attitude and approach and behavior is
going to be like it has nothing to do
with the size of Arunachal Pradesh and
sikim and Bhutan and it has absolutely
nothing to do with that
so let's not try and equate this land
area of this with the land area of that
that's not how things work we have a
tremendous amount of leverage over China
and and and it it really China is really
concerned about this China is rattled
right so that's the deal so we need to
use the Tibet issue Tibet is illegally
illegitimately occupied brutally
occupied by China is destroying Tibet's
culture the Tibetan language
they They they they have conducted
cultural endemic genocide in Tibet. They
have brutalized the people and this
continues and they so this needs to be
brought on in front of the world and we
need to leverage this as much as
possible. So uh we are doing the right
thing.
Okay. Malik said sorry for the stupid
question really. Okay. Let's see what
the question is. Uh why can't we have
high resolution cameras stationed on the
ground and many camera satellites which
monitor aerial threats? Uh doesn't
matter how much stealth capabilities it
has can be shot using high camera
station data and satellite realtime
tracking. Forgive my ignorance. No, it's
not. Look, you know what? It's actually
a very good question. This is the kind
of question that uh that forces you to
answer from first principles. What's the
set of differences between uh cameras
and radars and why are radars better
than cameras? I think these are the
question kinds of questions that
students need to ask and teachers need
to be able to answer such questions.
Right? It's not a stupid question. It's
actually a very good question. Right? So
the objective
is to detect aircraft, right? That's the
objective. Now like the Chinese have
this proverb. It doesn't matter what
color the cat is as long as it catches
mice, right? I don't care if the cat was
black or white or orange or whatever as
long as it catches mice. So then why? So
I don't care if it's a radar or a set of
cameras or whatever as long as it does
the best possible job in detecting
aircraft. Right. Right. So then the
question then is why do we why do
militaries prefer radars and why not
cameras? Is that a stupid question? It's
not a stupid question. It's a great
question. So the question then is that
we have to ask ourselves is what is it
that makes a good aircraft detection
system?
So what are the characteristics of a
good a useful aircraft detection system?
First of all, it should be able to
detect aircraft early.
If enemy aircraft are approaching my
country, I want as much warning time as
possible. I don't want to know about it
when it's like 3 seconds away. I want to
know about it when it is like still 500
km away. I need early warning. So, my
system should be able to detect aircraft
early.
That's one. Secondly, it should be
reliable. It should be able to catch
detect almost all the aircraft that are
coming towards me towards my country. It
should not work only with 50% of the
aircraft. It'll it'll catch 50% and 50%
will just sneak through. That doesn't
work. I want a very reliable robustly
reliable system.
Thirdly, uh I want my system to
to avoid false alarms. often a set of
balloons,
birthday balloons filled with helium
will be detected. H
there's this movie, not movie, there's a
song from the 1980s called 99 Lufta
balloon by a German singer called Nina
that is about this sort of scenario. So
I don't want my system to mistake clouds
or birds or balloons or other such
objects for enemy aircraft. It should
avoid false alarms. Then I want my
system to work 247 in all kinds of
weather, right? Whether it is snowy,
whether it is rainy, whether it's foggy,
whether it is nighttime, it should
should work. Okay? So different weather
patterns should not shut down my system.
Then I want my system
to show the exact location and the exact
speed of the incoming aircrafts,
right?
and and also I want my system to be able
to cover huge areas cheaply. I want my
system to be able to protect my entire
country without destroying my budget.
Yeah. So that's the characteristics of
of of a good reliable aircraft detection
system. Now let's consider cameras.
Do cameras work at night? Well, they can
if if there is light. So cameras only
work when there is light. So if my enemy
aircraft they have all their warning
lights, flashing lights on, then my
cameras will detect them. But if my
enemy aircraft which is coming towards
me has switched off all lights and it's
operating as stealthy as possible, my
camera won't work. So will the camera
work at night? Essentially no. Secondly,
will my cameras, even if I have a
thousand cameras, will they work in bad
weather, rain, snow, night? No, it won't
work. Thirdly, can my cameras see over
the horizon? The horizon if if you are
at at ground level is about what 7 miles
10 km 10 11 12 km that's the horizon can
my camera see over the horizon it can't
even if my if I have my camera at let's
say 50 m height it may still not see too
far away right uh so my cameras can't
see over the horizon now if I have a set
of cameras will they tell me at what
distance the aircraft is currently which
is which it has detected? No. Will it
tell me what direction it's coming in?
No. Is is is is a set of cameras good
for early warning like I want like if
it's 500 km away, I want I want to know
about it. No, it's not. Now, let's
consider radars. Do radars work at
night? Yes, they work at night. Do
radars work in bad weather? Radars work
in bad bad weather. Can radars see over
the horizon? Well, some types of radars
can see over the horizon. Okay.
depending on what what the type is. But
yeah, it can in principle see over the
horizon. Uh, does a radar show me the
distance that the aircraft is from me?
Yes, absolutely. It shows me exactly how
far the aircraft is. And is a radar
system good for early warning? It's
excellent. And then satellites.
Satellites also we can put cameras and
things on satellites. Do satellites work
at night? Yes, they work at night. Work
at night. Can satellites work in bad
weather? Yes. Can satellites see over
the horizon? Of course, they can see
over the horizon. Can satellites show
the distance? Yes. Are satellites good
for early warning? Very good. So you see
cameras, radar satellites, cameras don't
work. You can have a 10,000 cameras and
still radar will be better than cameras.
Do you understand?
So, so in in modern warfare, you use a
combination of net of of a network of
radars and satellite systems
for um your early warning system for
your aircraft detection system. Uh, of
course, stealth is a different story.
We'll we'll not discuss stealth over
here. um stealth also depending on the
type of radar and the power and all that
you can detect aircraft in principle
what air I mean how far the aircraft is
and what and so on uh so that's the deal
so essentially radar is like having
superpowered eyes that can essentially
see through walls in the darkness and
hundreds of kilometers away and cameras
are limited to what human eyes can see
on a on a on a clear day huge difference
so that's why in modern warfare we use a
combination of radars and satellites for
detecting aerial threats. So I think
it's an excellent question. I'm glad you
asked it and you gave me the opportunity
to explain the difference between these
things. Outstanding.
Okay.
Okay. Danush says, "What's happening
with India West ties? On the one hand,
reports say that a US India mini deal is
near. On the other hand, the NATO chief
is threatening India with secondary
sanctions. Lindsey Graham wants a 500%
tariff on India. Trump has given a
50-day warning to Putin to make a deal
or he will put 100% tariffs on the
nations the trade with Russia like
India. Well, I think you've seen my geo
strategy episode from yesterday, haven't
you? Uh but he then he also says India
is fully opening up to us and they
designated TRF the terrorist group
behind the pahalgam terror attack.
Right? They've designated designated TRF
as a terrorist group. So what's
happening and my important question is
the west really looking to really going
to sabotage the India relationship for
the sake of Ukraine. Wouldn't that still
be against their interests even though
they don't like India long term? This
has nothing to do with Ukraine.
The US India relationship doesn't exist
in the context of Ukraine. Ukraine is is
one of the factors. Sure. Uh one of the
factors that that they would like to use
to pressurize India with. So it's it's a
point of leverage. It's a pressure point
that they can you know deploy on demand
Ukraine. You did not support us on
Ukraine. You didn't you did not uh go
ahead with you know you did not
participate in western sanctions on
Russia visa v the Ukra in the context of
the Ukraine conflict and so on. That's
what they can do and that's how they can
use that as a negotiating tactic and
pressure point and leverage point uh
during negotiations. They can do that.
uh when it comes to this India US trade
deal, India categorically rejected US
pressure of the of this you know what
July 9 deadline. The Americans had
unilaterally given a July 9 deadline by
which India needs to agree to a deal
with the US and India categorically
rejected that we said that the deal is
we are not ready uh to accept all your
demands and we need to negotiate more so
we're going to extend the deadline.
Let's make it August one or whatever.
So, we have not capitulated to the US
demands and we have not gone ahead and
signed some kind of deal with the US.
The negotiations are still on. We are
negotiating really hard, right? And the
Americans are using all these pressure
tactics on us. Uh secondary sanctions,
NATO, the NATO chief is threatening
India. NATO is North Atlantic Treaty
Organization. Why don't you look into
matters related to the Atlantic region?
Why don't you keep mind your own
business and stay out of India? But no,
they won't do it, right? Because the
NATO chief is is a well, he's an asset
of the US. So the NATO chief is
threatening India with secondary
sanctions. Lindsey Graham, like you
said, wants 500% tariffs on India
because India is purchasing Russian oil.
Trump is also, you know, threatening
India with various tariffs, 100%
tariffs, uh because of trade with
Russia. U then they've gone ahead and
designated TRF as a terrorist group. So
obviously there's negotiations happening
and we have made a set of demands
conditions that need to be fulfilled and
they seem to be you know accepting some
conditions and giving giving us some of
the things we want. So maybe that's why
TRF has been designated as a terrorist
group. It's okay. They can designate TRF
as a terrorist group but they can create
50 other terrorist groups with with
other names and use them against India
through Pak via Pakistan. So that's no
big deal for the US. They've done this
played this game in the past. It's no
big deal. So it's it's a small it's not
some big huge victory for India that the
US has you know bureaucratically
put a rubber stamp on TRF terrorist
group. They can create a 100 more
terrorist groups tomorrow via Pakistan.
They've done that in the past
and uh Trump is saying India is fully
opening up to us. Really are we? No we
are negotiating. We are not opening up
to you and we will not accept uh India
is not going to accept US agricultural
demands that we uh bring we allow the
export of American agriculture and dairy
dairy products to India. We will not
accept that because there is poison.
They can poison their people. It's fine
but we will not accept that their GMO
stuff and all those patents Monsanto
patents and whatnot. No, that's not
going to happen. And that's what they
want because they want to vasalize
India. These are East India company
tactics that they're trying to use. Uh
so so India West ties aren't great.
Trump is trying to bully India to arm
twist India into accepting everything
like what he has done to Indonesia.
Right? He has turned Indonesia into a
total vasal. Utter Indonesia has had to
go down on its knees and accept whatever
the Americans said.
That's what's happened to Indonesia. We
are not going in the same direction. But
the relationship isn't great and yeah.
So, so that's the deal. Uh so the real
question you are asking is is the west
going to sabotage their relationship
with India for the sake of Ukraine. It
has nothing to do with Ukraine.
They are doing this to every country and
India is important because it's the
fourth largest economy first of all
and second of all it's important from
the perspective of the US
China rivalry.
Um
and that's why the US needs India on its
side. If in case there's a contingency
in the future, maybe a Chinese invasion
of Taiwan or or some kind of conflict um
involving China, North Korea, whatever,
in that case they want India on their
side. And India also feels that you know
China is a threat. So it's good to have
the US on our side. So that's the that's
the approach that's the deal. And the US
does need India on its side when it
comes to the matter of China. But they
would also like to extract as much out
of India when it comes to this these
trade and tariff this trade and tariff
war. So they are trying to extract as
much as they can gain as much as they
can from India and make India concede as
much as possible and India is playing a
very tough game. It's negotiating really
hard. Uh so it's going to take a while.
Maybe by the end of this year, you may
have some kind of trade deal, a full
final trade deal perhaps. Perhaps. And
maybe if we maybe by the time Trump's
patience may run out and I don't know,
he may throw some kind of tantrum
uh which may well which may be bad for
both sides perhaps. We'll have to see
about that. But let me remind you once
again, let me reiterate this has nothing
to do with Ukraine. The US doesn't care
about Ukraine. Ukraine is a disposable
asset for the for the US.
They're going to fight this war until
the last Ukrainian is alive and then
they will throw Ukraine into the trash
bin and take extract all the minerals as
much as they can and then maybe have
Poland become the next Ukraine. So
that's how you use Vasals, right? That's
how you use them as disposable assets
and they would like to turn India into
that and we are not going to have that
happen. So it's a tug of war right now
essentially. Uh it's nothing to do with
Ukraine like I said. Um and this will
continue and uh yeah the relationship
won't be great. It's not great anyway.
It's never been great. The US India
relationship. The US looks upon India as
as a as a colonized nation which we are.
I mean we are a colonized nation. We
have never decolonized and uh they would
like to maintain that. Then they would
like to perpetuate there and they would
like to strengthen that.
So yeah, it's going to be this is going
to be something we have to keep our eye
on eye on and I think every episode of
geost strategy there's going to be some
new development in this matter. So we're
going to keep an eye on that.
Okay. Sunmoon0877
says are travel vloggers getting paid by
other countries to bring down a nation.
Yeah, sure that can happen. Look, travel
vloggers are people, individuals who
generally are on YouTube, YouTubers, and
their content is travel content. Oh, I
went to so and so country and this was
my experience there. I ate this food and
I stayed in this hotel and I saw these
places and these were the kind of people
I met. Some are nice, some are not.
Whatever. That's a travel vlog. And if
you make it interesting, people will
watch, right? And there are many famous
travel vloggers. There are some not so
famous travel vloggers. Now, here's the
deal. Let's say you are a reasonably
popular travel vlogger and let's say you
are Mr. X. Okay.
And you are an Indian travel vlogger
and your viewers are mostly Indians,
right? So then if you are a nation like
China for example and you want Indians
to to have a good opinion of China, then
what if you're the Chinese government,
what you can do is you can approach this
Mr. X, whoever it is, through whatever
means, and propose a deal, then you know
what, Mr. X, we're going to sponsor your
trips to China. We're going to give you
business class flight tickets. We're
going to set you up in fivestar hotels,
and we're going to facilitate your
travel to whatever part of China uh we
would like you to visit. So, we want you
to make these many x number of trips to
China in a year, and you will visit
these places. We will give you the
itinary. We'll give you a guide. We'll
give make sure we'll arrange for your
travel and accommodation. We'll even pay
you a a salary
x number of dollars per month per trip.
So if you do one trip and you cover
let's say five cities, we're going to
pay you $10,000 or whatever the whatever
the amount is, you know, depending on
the person. In that way you can use
these Indian travel vloggers to
influence the mindset of Indians and
make it more pro-China.
That's one thing the Chinese can do.
Okay. Another thing the Chinese can do
is they can cultivate assets in India.
Not just travel vloggers.
For example, news readers, news anchors,
news analysts. I'm not naming anybody,
by the way. If you want me to name
somebody, I can actually name someone.
Would you like me to? So, I'm not sure
if this person is paid by the Chinese or
not. But, uh, it looks like this person
is very fond of China. So, let's let's
take a look at this person. Uh, that
person's name is SL Cantan.
So, let's let's Google this this person,
shall we? Um, I'll give you an example.
I am not saying this person is on the
payroll of China. Maybe maybe may not
be. I I don't have I'm not making a
definitive statement. SL
Canon.
This is an Indian person.
And if you see this person's Twitter,
it's all China, China, China, China,
China, China, China. Okay. Extremely uh
bullish on China. Russia and China.
Um, China and you know what? Who's the
Chinese ambassador to India? First of
all, one second.
Uh, Chinese ambassador. Okay. Chinese
ambassador to India. His name is Mr. Shu
Fihong. Uh, where's his Twitter? Twitter
over here. Now, let's take a look at Mr.
Fihong, the Chinese ambassador of India.
His Twitter Twitter timeline. Let's take
a look. Let's go to uh June.
Right now it's all Tibet propaganda
because of what's happened recently.
Tibet, Tibet, Tibet. But let's go to the
Manser over Yatra those days. Ah, there
we have it. Indian geopolitical analyst
SL Cantan. China has done a good job of
preserving Tibetan culture. So the
Chinese ambassador is promoting this
particular individual. So now let's go
to SL Kantan. Do we have his Twitter
thing over here? Oh, here it is.
Slantan. So this gentleman is an Indian
citizen very very pro-China. I am not
claiming that he is because I don't have
information. I'm not claiming that he is
paid by the Chinese government but he's
extremely pro-china. Let's let's search
for something. Okay.
Axai Chin. Axai Chin. What does Mr.
Kantan have to say about Axai Chin?
Let's see.
India, China border, etc. LA
um what else has he said about Axai?
Here we have it. See what he says here.
Axai Chin never belonged to India or the
British. That's what Mr. SL Kantan has
to say. So he is taking China's side on
this. Look here. India will never get
Axai Chin. What a delusional idea.
Do you want to have peaceful relations
with China or are we too blinded by
hatred and fanatical hubris? So as you
can see this gentleman Mr. SL Kantan.
Uh he is extremely pro-China
which raises a lot of questions from my
perspective about what is he up to. Is
he simply somebody who is in great love
with China? Has he been honey trapped
somehow by the Chinese or is he
potentially hypothetically
being paid by the Chinese?
Hypothetically I am not claiming he is
but is he? I think the government of
India needs to look into people like
these
these people they develop big followings
because of the push that's given to them
by the Chinese official accounts like
the government of China ambassador of
China and there are other Chinese assets
there are this this French there are
French people who spend the whole day
just like Mr. Russell Canton praising
China on Twitter and they gain big
followings. These people mysteriously
get get big gain big followings in
Twitter and then they all work together
and amplify each other's content you
know that's how it works. So there are
French people who do that there are
there's this Indian gentleman who does
that Mr. SL Kantan and so on. Uh so I
think the government of India needs to
just look to these these accounts. I
mean how does an Indian person go out on
Twitter and say that Axai
will will never belong to India. It
never belong to India. India will never
get a chin. Really? Have you seen the
map of India official map of India? Have
you read history? But he clearly takes
the Chinese side all the time. Um so the
question we have to ask ourselves is
that are people like Mr. SL Canton being
paid by China for their services
or are they simply u in love with China
or have they hypothetically been honey
trapped or are they hypothetically being
blackmailed for some reason because they
may have done something not very wise in
the past I don't know so there are many
examples like these and it's very very
common for people to be used as assets
by foreign nations by enemy nations in
this manner it's very easy you will not
find any Chinese person who lives in
China doing the same thing for India,
you know, telling the Chinese citizens
that, you know, India is a great nation.
We we should not fight with India and we
need to return Axajin to India or
whatever. You will never see a Chinese
person doing that. But in India, you
have these people who work for China
either u willingly or or hypothetically
being paid. I don't know about that but
whatever you know. So we have plenty of
possible enemies within. So it's not
just travel vloggers, it is news
readers, news journalists, journalists.
Recently the Chinese government had
reopened this manser over Kaashra,
right? Very very very kindly and a whole
bunch of Indian journalists were invited
to Tibet and some of them went and
praised Tibet you know the Chinese
government's uh um whatever it is doing
in Tibet and so on. Some of them did
that some of them them did not. Some of
them could just be useful idiots. I'm
not saying all of them are useful idiots
or idiots at all but some of them could
have been useful for idiots but some of
them may possibly be working for China
possibly potentially. So yeah we have
these problems in India and I think it's
time that the government takes a closer
look at these things because this is a
matter of national security and the
China is our number one threat. Right.
Right.
Okay. Senaphile says, "I'm a final year
I'm a CS final year student. Uh
currently seeing all these layoffs by
Microsoft and these big companies due to
AI. What should I plan for the future?
Now that I'm uh seeing all these IT jobs
being wiped out by AI in the near
future, right? So you are a CS computer
science final year student and you're
obviously concerned about what's
happening because of AI. AI could
replace everything. There are big
layoffs by Microsoft and various other
companies because of AI replacement
because of a lot of uh a lot of job uh
descriptions being replaced by AI tools,
AI agentic tools and whatnot. So what
should somebody in caphiles
situation and position do to plan for
the future because yeah it jobs could
get wiped out by AI. So look, AI is here
to stay as far as we know and a
significant substantial portion of of
routine and repetitive work, you know,
process oriented routine work,
repetitive work in IT, tasks in IT of
this nature are at high risk of being
automated by AI. Okay. And it it's
especially applies to uh you know roles
like data entry and tech support
and uh you know low-level programming
work, low-level quality assurance work,
QA that sort of thing. uh and I've seen
a report by I don't know Goldman Sachs
or whatever McKenzie I think whoever it
was and they they predicted that by 2030
about 30% of of uh white collar jobs
including IT could be heavily automated
by AI. So I think that's a very
conservative estimate they're giving 30%
by 2030 of IT jobs. Uh so that's that's
there
is there going to be total collapse of
IT employment? I don't think IT
employment will see a total collapse but
a lot of
uh repetitive jobs will be automated and
many IT roles will be augmented possibly
by AI not eliminated. So the skill
requirements will change the focus will
will move towards higher level work,
creative work, strategic work and so on.
Uh so what you need to do you know if
you if you are in AI if you are in IT
you need to be able to continuously
learn you need to be able to
continuously upskill
and you have to
you need to be able to hopefully work in
in roles that need human qualities that
need leadership qualities strategic
depth uh cross-disciplinary insight
maybe hands-on requirements ments
hand hands-on work that sort of thing.
Uh for example, cyber security strategy,
ethical hacking, all of this needs uh
adaptation, right? It needs creativity,
it needs human judgment. Probably AI
can't take that. Uh that's one example.
If you are a product manager, if you are
a relationship manager, if you're a
project manager, you need to do complex
integration, you need to do strategic
development. uh you need to collaborate
with with various teams, you need to
provide leadership. Uh then you have
prompt engineering which is a very AI
AIcentric task. So I think that the
thing is that you know there is no job
that is AI proof but the safest careers
are those that involve creativity, they
involve leadership and they involve
adapt adaptability. They need human
judgment and so much more. uh and
obviously the human skills like
interpersonal skills if you can blend
them with technical skills and so on uh
that is what uh is going to be you know
AI proof hopefully in in the in the long
run in the future. So if you are a final
year CS computer science student in
India, I can assure you that your degree
will not give you the skills needed to
survive
long term when AI takes over and AI is
taking over gradually.
So you need to do this of your own
initiative.
You need to acquire uh these abilities,
this this aptitude, these set of skills
on your own.
Otherwise you you may not you know
survive the AI the the AI takeover of
IT. I think a lot of the Indian IT
companies and firms they are not very
adaptable. They are not keeping up with
the times.
They are stuck in old ways of thinking
because Indian students in the products
of Indian education system are are they
can't think differently. Uh they can't
innovate in so much more. So I think the
Indian IT industry is at great risk. Uh
so yeah that's how that's what you have
to do you know able to be to be able to
uh withstand the the coming of AI the a
the AI takeover and and automation of so
many tasks that's what you need to do
okay NCERTT what's your take on changes
in NCERT of the Mgal period many left
historians are saying that Hindu kings
too plundered and looted plundered and
looted the the country the territory and
temples giving examples of some king of
Kashmir and talking ill about
Maharaj to hell with the left historians
that's I mean I think it's time to say
that we should not
take them seriously anymore
they'll keep on repeating these lies now
every time they repeat a lie and it gets
published somewhere do we have to come
on come back and respond to their lies
no ignore them completely stop
discussing them when you stop talking
about somebody they get margin
generalized, right? We need to simply
exclude them from the conversation.
These left historians,
all of us. Enough of this nonsense. Of
course, there was warfare in ancient
India,
right? Which country has not had
warfare? If you have two neighboring
kingdoms, obviously, there'll be
rivalries. So, what's wrong with that?
There's going to be conquest.
Who was Samudra Gupta? He was a
conqueror.
wasn't he? He conquered the whole of
India by defeating kings. He killed some
kings. He he captured their territories.
Um so does it mean that we are evil
civilization?
Have you seen other countries in their
histories? What they did to civilians?
We never did. We never mistreated
civilians. My point is I don't want to
discuss this again. My point is let's
talk about NCERTT. So I'm hearing that
NCERT textbooks have been revamped,
revised and now they uh more accurately
uh reflect the true history of India.
That's what I hear. I saw some examples
on on Twitter yesterday and today and it
was great. So I think finally we have
done something good. The government of
India has finally got its act together.
took them 11 plus years but it looks
like the NCERT textbooks are good now
and they are they they are now
respectful towards the history of India
the culture of India and they are no
longer showing distorted nonsense I
think it's not just about the Mughal
period I think it's overall that they
have been you know um improved
significantly vastly I haven't seen the
Mughal part I don't care about the
Mughal period and I I haven't seen any
examples of what's written written in
the NC textbooks about the Mughal period
but whatever I saw was was pretty good.
So I think it's a very welcome
development. I have been saying for I
don't know how many years that India
needs to do something about this. So I
think we are finally taking steps in
that direction and I'm very pleased to
hear that. So that's all I can say about
it right now. I I don't have any
textbooks in my hands. I don't think I'm
going to take the time to buy textbooks
and study them and see what has been
changed and maybe get examples of older
textbooks and old version new version. I
don't know how to do that do that but I
I think that uh we have taken some very
welcome steps steps uh when it comes to
u revamping the NCERT textbook so I
think that's great very good
okay what next do we have Sharma 108x
says what are the origins of the Kushans
Google says that the Kusan empire
emerged from the UAG a nomadic group
from central Asia who conquered Bactria
the 2nd century BC where the central
Asian or Chinese and how did they
conquer much of northern India? Okay.
So, first of all, my dear friends,
Google is not an answer engine. It's a
search engine. When you search something
on for something on Google, it gives you
a whole list of search results which are
websites and it is those websites that
will give you various answers. Of
course, Google now seems to have an AI
feature which summarizes everything. So,
it may be giving you a certain answer.
Uh, now here's the deal. You you this is
what you've said said over here that the
Koshans according to Google emerged from
the UAG a nomadic group from central
Asia who conquered Bactrea. So we have
two terms here UAG and Bactria.
Bactria these are all foreign terms they
use okay foreign terms they will use
foreign terms so that you get all
confused.
Bactria is Gandhar.
Present day Afghanistan. Historical
Gandhar. That's Bactria.
Okay. So these gentlemen, they conquered
Gandhar, northwest India in the 2nd
century BC. They did not conquer on some
day on the 2nd century BC. The whole of
Gandhar. They started making inroads
slowly into Gandhar in the around the
2nd century BC. Now the question is
about the origins of the Kushans
the UAG. Who are these UAG? It's a
Chinese name. Why don't they use the
Indian name instead of the Chinese name?
Why? Why does this western search engine
use a Chinese name instead of the actual
Indian name? What was the Indian name of
this group? It was the Tushara people.
The Tushara people. Let's let's Google
this. Who are the Tushara people?
Yeah. What will what will our friend
Google have to say about this?
Who were the Tushara
people?
Taras also known as Tukharas or
Tokarians
were an Indo-Uropean tribe or group of
tribes that settle in Central Asia,
Turkmanistan, Afghanistan. They are
mentioned in ancient Index like the
Mahabharat, the Amletcha, barbarians
etc. Relationship to Tokarians. The term
tokarian is also used al often used
interchangeably with tokara tokarian
languages tarim basin and so on and the
Chinese they called them the da ui so
that's the tushara people the so-called
tokarian tokarian people the tushara
kingdom and so on so there's the
Wikipedia page obviously it's not
entirely reliable o ever
uh
What does it say over here? The so-cal
tokarians. Now for the Tokarians,
they're going to have a different
Wikipedia page which is separate from
the Tushara people. The Tokarians
uh so I will not go into this but let's
quickly Google Tokarians shall we?
Tokarian people they lived in the Tarim
River basin. Okay. Now to understand
what that is we have to go to the map.
So let me quickly show you the map.
Where's the tarim river basin
is? Okay, here's the map. Tarim the
tarim river basin is this region. Okay,
present day so-called shinjang. If we
Google tarim
tarim river basin, it's this region over
here. The tarim river is an ancient
pretty big river that flows over here.
And it is in the tarim river basin that
the uh or the tushara people lived. It
is right now if you go there it's it's
the Takla Makan desert but in the past
it was it was pretty green. So that's
where these people lived the Tushara
people. Now let me show you something
else. The Tarim Basin mummies.
Uh one second give me a second. Give me
a second. For that we have to go back to
Google and we were looking at at
tokarians. Now we will look at the tarim
river basin. Tarim mummies.
Tarim mummies. You know because the
region is so dry the people who are
buried there uh their bodies are very
well preserved and if you look at these
people they look very western okay that
their their facial features etc. As you
can see, this this ancient lady, she has
a light color or maybe red colored hair,
you know, ginger hair and uh this is
another person.
Um so, you know, they have found lots of
remains of these people. They were
typically pretty tall people, fair
skinned, blonde or redhaired people. Uh
they they used to have these tattoos.
This is another person, another lady.
5,000 years old perhaps. This is another
lady here. These are reconstructions
uh possibly European looking. But if you
uh this is another gentleman who passed
away a long time ago. So these are the
Tarim River basin mummies. If you look
at their culture,
if you look at their culture, despite
them looking European, they are very
Indian. And let me show you some
something else which will be surprising.
Okay. Okay, the tokarian language
tokarian script for example let's go to
omniglot
let's see the tokaran script so this is
about
um how old is the tokaran script first
of all what does our friend Wikipedia
have to say
8th century etc
and so on so let's go back to the to the
omglot tokquarian script what does this
look like The token alphabet is like
this. Uh
these are the vowels.
And how do you write the concerns? Kaka
gaasha.
I think it sounds shockingly Indian,
doesn't it?
Um
so that's the tarim script. It goes kaka
gaga just like any other Indian script.
And if you look at the
gods they worshiped, those were Indian
gods. And if you look at the genetics of
the Tarim, Tarim people, they had blonde
hair and red hair and whatnot and
whitish skin. Genetics are all R1 A1A,
very Indian, culturally Indian,
genetically Indian, religious
for what religion was essentially a form
of Hinduism.
Um
so yeah that that's that's that is the
origin of the Kushana people.
Very interesting right? Really
interesting. So then the question is
where the centralization of Chinese
definitely not Chinese. You could call
them possibly the eastern most skitians.
Uh so they most likely were descendants
of Indians who were who traveled out of
India thousands of years ago. We've had
many migrations out of out of India. The
first recorded example of a migration
out of India is the aftermath of the
battle of the 10 kings in which all the
defeated clans were expelled out of
India by king Diwadas the victor.
Uh yeah. So, so the the origin was most
likely Indian but they spent thousands
of years out of out of India which is
why they they accumulated they they
absorbed various foreign genetics also
I'm pretty sure right now why did these
gentlemen the the Kushans the the why
did they reinvade India why is that it
is because of the emergence of the Huns
the Hunas so once again let's go to the
map
and the huns about about 2,500 years ago
they emerged out of the present region
of Mongolia. Okay. Uh
and they started expanding westwards and
southwards and the Kusans or who lived
in this region the Tushara people who
lived in the Tarim region they were
forced to flee from the Huns because the
Hoons were more powerful. So the Kushans
fled westwards and southwards and
westwards and southwards you had the
skithians who were already living here.
So the skithians were forced to flee
from the Kushans because the Kushians
were more powerful. So the Huns
expanded. They were more powerful than
than the Kushans. So the Kushans fled
southwest. The Kushans were more
powerful than the Skithians who were in
the southwest. So they had to flee into
India. So that's how the Skian invasion
of India happened. And a couple of
centuries later the Kusans also entered
India and conquered India. And uh
neither the Kushans nor the Skithians
were culturally different from Indians
which is why they assimilated very
harmoniously into Indian society.
Right? The Skitians they established
various great kingdoms in India. the
northern satrups, the the western
satrups, the great Mahakhatrapas who
ruled out of Sabrashtra and Gujarat and
controlled uh our trade with the Romans.
Yeah. And uh the the Satraps were
shvites, servants and uh
and devotees of of Lord Shiva. And the
Koshans they were more in the north.
Kaneshka had this great empire. So yeah,
that's the story and that's the origins
of the Koshans.
Okay. Um,
next question is about Okay. It's by
Sunm Moon0877.
Can we sue all these higher higher hand
brands for copying our culture,
clothing, accessories, etc. without
giving us credit for it? On top of that,
it's 200% more expensive. So there was
this controversy recently about Prada or
whoever who had who have copied the
Indian kulapuri chapel and now these
western models are wearing those
kulapuri chapel on their feet and it's
it's priced at god knows what super
expensive price in India if you buy a
kapuri chapel it may cost you what 200
bucks 200 rupees or 500 rupees or
whatever reasonably cheap good quality
hopefully uh but the prada thing will be
obviously 10 times maybe 100 times more
expensive so it's an example of cultural
theft Of course, it's an example of
cultural theft and there are lots of
different forms of cultural theft. The
west has appropriated yoga and we have
done nothing about it. That's cultural
theft. Of course, uh just just uh
establishing a world yoga day is not
enough to save India from cultural
theft. You have to establish establish a
world yoga standards institute. But we
have never bothered to do that. So today
you have all kinds of
variations of yoga like dog yoga and hot
yoga and goat yoga and beer yoga and
drunk yoga and god knows what nonsense
they have ruined yoga the west um you
don't have that with kung fu you don't
have any non-Chinese variations of kung
fu today but you have all kinds of
non-Indian variations of yoga today so
that has been stolen when it comes to u
things like pranayam the west calls it
either box breeding or cardiac coherence
breathing So they've digested the the
the technique and now they've given it
given it fake western names. So new
practitioners will never even know that
it's actually something that came from
India. So the the west has a history of
doing this and they will keep on doing
that. So how do we stop this from
happening? By by owning the fact that we
are the originators. Our civilization is
the originator of all these uh of things
like yoga and pranayam and whatnot. To
do that you have to establish our
versions of the Shaolin temple. The
Shaolin temple is the global authority
of what kung fu is and what kung fu
cannot be. Similarly we need to have
world yoga standards institute in India
which will decide and determine what
constitutes yoga and what does not
constitute yoga and pranayam and so on.
That's one example. We need to also own
ayurvea because you know ashwagandha and
whatn not is now being digested by the
west. It's being stolen. And when it
comes to our clothing and all that, that
also will be copied and appropriated by
the west, it's it's bound to happen. Uh
there's not much we can do about
clothing
um and and styles of footwear and all
that. You can't really sue anybody for
drawing inspiration loosely or not so
loosely from from our traditions. I
don't think there's much we can do about
that, right? I mean we have even if you
look at India, if you look at Bollywood,
how much have has Bollywood stolen from
the west?
How many songs have Bollywood
uh lyricists stolen from western songs?
It goes both ways.
The the amount of theft is staggering.
Many of many Indians don't even know how
many of these songs originated in the
west and they were stolen by Indians.
Kishor Kumar stole that song. What's it
what's it called? Om Shanti Om from a
singer and songwriter for the West
Indies. A guy who never got credit for
that
and so many other examples. There's an
Elvis Presley song Margarita
which was which became some some Hindi
song from a 1960s or 70s movie.
uh
Saira Banu was the actress in the movie
if I remember Juka Aman and so many many
more more recent examples. So yeah
that's that's you know there's some
things you can do about this and some
things we simply can't do. So when it
comes to the theft of yoga and pranayam
I'm sure we can do a lot about that if
the government decides to wake up. When
it comes to stealing Kapuri chapels and
various kinds of Indian dresses and all
that, I don't think there's a lot we can
do about it.
Yeah.
Okay.
Rahul Durak says in the movie
Interstellar, they have shown a device
that can make a human hibernate for
years on the on on trot on the trot.
What is it based on?
That's a great movie. Interstellar, one
of the few movies that I liked this
century, 21st century,
and probably one of the best science
fiction movies I've seen. So in
interstellar, the the premise is that
what's the premise? Yeah, you travel
from the earth all the way to some other
stellar system and then yeah, so there's
a long journey and because the journey
is so long, it may take I don't know how
many years. You you do sleep. It's
called hypersleep or cryosleep or
something. So uh I think the the it's
based on hibernation. So on earth we
have many animals especially those that
live in very cold regions of the earth
that hibernate. For example, if you're a
bear in in northern Asia or maybe North
America or whatever, if you're a bear,
let's say you're a grizzly bear in North
America and uh it gets really cold in
the winter. So what grizzly bears will
do is that they will eat salmon, those
those big fish with with orange flesh.
They'll eat salmon. They'll gorge
themselves on salmon and become really
really heavy, hefty, fat. And then when
the winter when the winter comes, these
bears will just go into their their den
and sleep it off. They'll sleep for like
five, six months. And when the and and
it's continuous sleep. There's no waking
up for all those months. And then once
once the winter is over, the bear will
wake up and that fat bear that went in
is all loose and thin and it's burned
off all the fat it accumulated. So that
is a natural process that we have on the
planet. It's called hibernation. Many
species undergo hibernation to survive
the winter and it's something that can
theoretically be used to have humans
sleep with a lower metabolic rate for
possibly long periods of time. So that's
one concept hibernation which already
exists. It's a biological phenomenon.
The other phen the other concept is that
you know if you lower the temperature of
the body then you can really slow down
the met metabolism of the body and the
aging of the body. For example when you
have organ transplants.
Let's say somebody is receiving a heart
from somebody who just who's a organ
donor and who died. So you have to take
the heart out of the person who died
immediately and transport it as fast as
possible to the recipient who will take
the heart because their heart has failed
for whatever reason. So to do that you
have to bring the heart the temperature
of this of this donor heart as close to
zero as possible without freezing it. So
maybe around 4 5° centigrade. If you
freeze it, it it's going to destroy the
organ because ice crystals will form
which are needle like they'll poke holes
into the cells. So you want to bring the
temperature to maybe four, five degrees.
I'm not sure what the exact temperature
is, but as low as possible without
freezing it, without the formation of of
uh of water crystals, ice crystals. So
if you do that, then the metabolism
slows down and the organ doesn't undergo
cell death.
Similarly, if somebody uh if somebody is
is receiving a heart, you need to bring
their body's temperature down as as low
as possible so that uh you know there
are no complications. And when people u
for example, if somebody drowns in in
freezing water, they could be under
water for 20 30 minutes and they can
still be revived because at that low
temperature the body doesn't die that
fast. So these are the various concepts
that you have and you can package those
into this science fiction concept called
hypers sleep or cryosleep.
So it's not something that actually
exists, you know, uh it's
uh but potentially in the future you
could perhaps make something like that
happen because if you want to travel
several light years, a process that
maybe at 95% of the speed of light will
take maybe I don't know let's say you
want a person to survive a 100red-year
voyage in space, whatever distance it
is. Then obviously you want the person
to be as unchanged as possible when they
reach the destination. So for that you
will need some form of hibernation
combined with low temperatures so that
the body doesn't age and the person
person doesn't really age and and so on.
So that's a science fiction concept
that's hypersleep or cryosleep and
that's the and and the device they
showed was some kind of pod in which the
person will will be
you know made to sleep in and once they
go to sleep the person will be cooled
down or and they will undergo cryosleep.
So that's the device they have shown and
it's based on these concepts.
Okay.
What else do we have? We have a few more
questions. Let's talk some physics for a
change. It's been a while. So YJA likes
to ask very interesting physics
questions. If we annihilate the
assumption that the universe is roughly
homogeneous in very large scales, can we
eliminate the need for dark energy and
Hubble tension on it all at once?
Also can you tell us your views on
whether quintessence whether or not
quintessence as dark energy is probable?
Okay so uh there is this fundamental
assumption in cosmology that the
universe is homogeneous and isotropic on
the largest scales. This is uh a
fundamental assumption in cosmology.
Uh so imagine that the universe is a
gigantic
chocolate chip cookie.
Let's let's Google a chocolate chip
cookie so that you get the get what I'm
trying to say. Okay.
Chocolate chip chip cookie.
So what does a chocolate chip cookie
look like? It looks like this, right?
It's got these chocolate chips all over
it.
Right? These are chocolate chip cookies.
So imagine that the universe we live in
is a huge chocolate chip cookie. And
it's a huge one. Okay, not small one,
but huge one. And imagine you're looking
at this chocolate chip cookie from very
far away. So when you are close to the
surface of this chocolate chip cookie,
you can see all the individual chocolate
chips and you can see the the dough,
right? But when you go far enough,
when you go significantly far away, you
will no longer be able to see those
little chocolate chips and it will look
very uniform
and the chocolate chips will essentially
merge into a brown brown thing. So from
far away, you can't discern the
individual chocolate chips, but but you
can see the brown color.
So from a from a significant distance if
you are far enough you will see roughly
the same amount of chocolate chips
everywhere and that's the assumption
that we make okay uh that on large
enough scales the universe is roughly
the same everywhere.
Now we have two big mysteries that are
being mentioned by Yajjnulka. One is
dark energy and the other is the Hubble
tension. So what is dark energy? Now if
we look if we look at the universe look
at galaxies that are far away and so on
we notice that the universe is expanding
and the universe is expanding faster and
faster and the further an object away is
away from us the f faster it is going
away from us and we can measure the the
the speeds and so on using red shift and
other things you know uh so it's like a
balloon that's being blown up with
increasing speed so we can see that
something is causing the expansion of
the uni this universe this accelerated
expansion of the universe and that's
what we call dark energy we have no idea
what it is no idea we call it dark
energy that's one thing then there's
something called Hubble tension so when
we measure how fast the universe is
expanding using different methods we get
different answers so imagine I stand up
against my background and I have two
measuring scales so I I take one
measuring scale and I measure my height
it says 62 two and I use the other scale
it says 64
what should be just one one answer right
but it's but but I have two scales that
are given giving me two different
answers slightly different one is saying
62 and is saying 64 something is wrong
so that's that's the that's the Hubble
tension okay
so
some cosmologists some physicists have
wondered what if this fundamental
assumption is wrong what if the universe
isn't really uniform and isotropic on
large distance scales. So let's say we
are not living on a uniform chocolate
chip but we are living in a spot where
there are very few chocolate chips. This
is huge void that we are living in.
Okay, empty region. If you're living in
this pretty empty region which is very
less dense, the density is very less
then maybe the light that's traveling to
us from distant galaxies, it may behave
differently than we may expect if the
universe is homogeneous and isotropic.
So if we are living in this very special
low density region
then the apparent deceleration that we
see might just be or whatever speed of
light we see or whatever measurements we
are able to make they may be
incorrect or they may be illusions
because of the unusual location that we
are in and maybe the measurement
disagreements that are happening are
because that are because we are not
accounting for our special position.
in the universe. So, special location in
the universe, right? Uh so that that's
the that's the question that uh some
physicists have asked. Uh but the fact
is that there is no evidence that we are
that the planet earth and the solar
system and the Milky Way galaxy are
located in some very incredibly special
perfectly positioned region in the
universe. And we have plenty of evidence
from other observations like the cosmic
microwave background edition etc. which
do indicate very strongly that the
universe is indeed uniform and isotropic
on large scales.
So it's it's a pretty good question to
ask and uh
and if you annihilate this assumption
that the universe is roughly how all
that then it could indicate that but you
need other evidence to back it up that
we are indeed loc located located in
some uh special region of space
otherwise it doesn't really make sense.
So it's an interesting idea that that
some physicists are exploring but we
need way more evidence to actually take
this more seriously. Most of the
evidence that we have, observational
evidence, it points to the universe
being genuinely more or less roughly uh
uniform uh homogeneous and isotropic in
all directions, right? At the largest
scales. Uh so we actually do need to
figure out what dark energy actually is
and we do need to solve the big question
of the Hubble tension through some other
means. It's like detective work
actually. And maybe we need to look into
this from different perspectives. may be
perspectives that people may not have
thought about. For example, there is
this theory by Dr. Subashk who has
appeared on my podcast a few times. Uh
that the universe may not be
threedimensional or fourdimensional. It
may be e-dimensional where E is
the special number 2.8 whatever, right?
That's an interesting. It's a fractal
dimensional universe. Well, that's
interesting, isn't it? So, we need to
look at it uh you know look at things
from outside the box or maybe out of the
box approaches or whatever. What
whatever approaches we've been taking
for the longest time, they aren't really
working in physics. Uh now there's
another question about quintessence,
right? Uh so we discussed what is uh
dark energy? It's something that is
causing this our universe to expand
faster and faster. This uh accelerating
expansion of this universe. So there is
something that is causing it. Obviously,
we don't know what it is, but we call it
dark energy. So that's where
quintessence comes in. So quintessence
is possible is possibly this this some
kind of special invisible energy that
fills up all of space just like air
fills up a room. But this energy is
everywhere in in our universe which
means that it is right here in this room
with me. Quintess essence comes from um
Greek
quint essence the fifth essence. The
Greeks believed that everything was made
up of what? Earth, air, water, fire and
and and what ether or some fifth fifth
essence, fifth thing. So that's
quintessence. Uh
so quintessence is supposed to be
something that uh that pushes things
apart. It doesn't pull things together.
It pushes things apart. It's like an
anti-gravity kind of force. That's what
it believed. It's like an invisible
force that is constantly stretching
space apart. But there is something
special about quintessence. Its value
changes over time. Its strength changes
over time. So in the early universe,
earlier universe, you had more dark
energy than dark matter. But today you
have more way more dark energy than dark
matter. So maybe it's because the the
strength of quintessence has changed
over time. It's like a switch whose
settings you can change, you know, a fan
switch or something, that sort of thing.
So that's what quintessence is. I think
it's an interesting theory. uh but uh we
need more research to it's still a
hypothesis. We have no observational
evidence of it. So that is what
quintessence is. I think it is an
interesting theory and we should
certainly um examine it. I have taken it
pretty seriously in the past. So yeah,
quintessence is is a an interesting
theory that could potentially uh throw
some light on what dark energy is.
Okay, Yajjala again says, "Does the K
formula give us hints about a new
understanding underlying theory of
physics?"
Uh, the K formula, it's it's something
that uh was discovered in the 1980s by a
Japanese physicist whose surname is Koh.
So, let's let's look up what the formula
looks like. It's it's a relationship
between various kinds of lepttons.
Leptons are very nice particles. One of
the the lightest lepton is the electron.
So, k formula.
This is particle physics which is
interesting which is something I've not
looked into for a very long time but
here we have it. Uh this is the coe
formula. I'm not sure what Carl Bran
Bran is. Uh this is what the formula
looks like. M mu and m towel.
Uh generally it's inverted. It's the
generally you know the the the
denominator is on is the numerator
actually usually.
So what's the deal in the particle
world? We have these players
particles called lepttons. They are the
lightweight members of the particle
family. So just take a look at the
formula. This is what it looks like. Now
let's take that off the screen. Right?
So uh the lepttons are you could call
them the lightweight members of the
particle family. You have the electron,
you have the muon, and you have the tow.
These three particles, the electron is
is super light and we all know the
electron because you know electricity
they orbit nuclei and all that, right?
The muon is a heavier cousin of the
electron. It's about 200 times more
massive than the electron. And then
there's a tow particle which is about 3
and a half thousand times heavier than
the electron. These three these are
three leptons. So this Japanese
physicist ku he discovered this
relationship that we just saw. Let's put
it back on the screen. uh between
between the masses of the leptons.
So me is the mass of the electron.
Actually, this is the correct coid
formula. That's the one that I'm
familiar with. I'm not familiar with
this one. This is this is an inverted
version of it, but this is the one. So m
is the mass of the electron. M mu is the
mass of the muon and m to is the mass of
the toao particle. In the denominator we
have the three square roots added up and
then the sum is squared and and this
fraction its value is very close to 2x3.
So it's it's pretty weird actually. I
mean it's a pretty strange and unusual
uh pattern that Mr. Ko that Dr. Ky
discovered. So imagine that you have
you you have a school you have a
classroom in which you have like let's
say 50 students and you take three kids
at random and you measure the heights of
those three kids and then you and then
you find that if you combine them in a
very specific mathematical way you
always get the three same number. Is
that a coincidence or is that more than
a coincidence? And that's exactly the
question as to what is this why why are
the the the ratios of the fraction the
these numbers why why is why do they
have this specific relationship and does
it uh actually hint at something deeper
is the question right is there some kind
of hidden symmetry in nature that we
haven't discovered yet and is the ki
formula hinting towards this this uh
symmetry that's one question maybe is
there some kind of fundamental theory
underlying theory that explains why the
particles have the masses that they do
because we don't know why particles have
the masses that they have. Why does the
top quark have so and so mass? Why does
the strange quark have so and so mass?
Why does the electron have this mass?
And why does the proton have a slightly
different mass from the neutron and so
why what is what is behind these
constants that we have in physics? Then
maybe the ki formula is is showing us
some kind of direction. Is there some
extra dimensions that the koid formula
is hinting towards? So we don't have the
answers right now but it's it's an
unsolved puzzle that that this formula
is but it it uh is pretty interesting
and maybe it's giving us hints towards a
new underlying theory of physics maybe
new symmetries maybe a new underlying
theory maybe extra dimensions we don't
quite know right now but it's something
that's pretty interesting and worth
investigating. Yeah.
Okay, Miranka Seeker Biswas says some as
someone who's working on a project in
muan's catin tomography I've observed
that many physics PhD programs today a
shifting focus from core theoretical and
experimental physics towards programming
machine learning and simulation tools
like comsaw
how should we view this trend as a ne as
a necessary evolution of this discipline
discipline or as a departure from the
foundational rigor of physics research
it's very much a departure from the
it's it's a dilution
in the way physics is done and that's
something you see all over the place. Um
if you are in theoretical physics if you
then you should be taught theoretical
physics from first principles properly.
Um you know programming and whatnot it's
it's a good it's a good set of skills to
have.
There's no harm in learning programming
if you're a theoretical physicist or or
any kind of physicist. it can help but
um it's shifting the focus away from the
real job of a physicist. um even if
you're an experimentalist, yeah, sure,
programming can help you,
but uh it's it's something that's an
addendum to what you're supposed to
learn. But today, it's you see this all
over the place, you know, and it's not
just today. Even 25 years ago,
if you did a for example, a master's
degree in in physics, half of the
syllabus sometimes in some universities
would be electronics.
So it's always been that way. It's it's
especially in India.
But if you I'm sure if you go to a high
quality top quality worldass physics
department, you won't you won't see such
things. They will offer you all these
additional uh credits for things like
you know programming and machine
learning and whatnot but it's not the
core uh syllabus. It's not the core
thing that you're learning. So I think
it's it's it's diluting what you're
supposed to learn and it's it's
problematic. It's not really a necessary
evolution of the discipline. These are
tools and skills that can help you solve
problems, but that's something you learn
once you have mastered the the core
subject matter, right? It's it's
definitely a departure from the
foundational rigor of physics research.
and and if you spend too much time doing
all of that, when are you going to do
the actual physics? So, I think it's
it's problematic and I I I do not
support this. I do not approve of this.
Okay. Blind Julka says, "Does a person
born blind see the color black or does
that person see nothing, not even black?
Can colors be really explained
completely to such a person?" Um
it's like asking you know look a person
who is born blind doesn't even know what
vision is.
They don't know what colors are.
They don't even know what sight is, what
that experience is, what that perception
is.
It's like
um you know for example if you have a
sheet of paper it's essentially
two-dimensional and if that's the only
experience you have you have you will
never know what three dimensions are
and once you three once you see three
dimensions
it changes your world view completely.
Now we see the world in three
dimensions. Can we imagine what four
what a fourdimensional universe would
look like? We can't imagine it. We can
draw
representations of that on paper, but we
can't sense it, feel it, imagine it,
perceive it. We can intellectualize it
by drawing something that looks like
four dimensions on a piece of paper, but
we can't really experience it.
Similarly, a person who is born blind
can't really experience what sight is,
what colors are, what light is. They
will not know what is black or red or
whatever. So I'm not sure they see
anything or perceive anything but if if
you can give them the the gift of sight
then they will the world will be changed
like never before.
Um so yeah that's probably how it is.
Uh Ritik Paw says, "As you've been
studying geopolitics and history for
many years, can you please tell us in
your opinion what are the three which
are the three most which are the top
three most powerful countries or empires
in the past 10,000 years that were ab
absolutely dominant or ruled the world
for the longest time? No empire has
ruled the world." Okay? No empire in the
past. You did not have the technological
prowess or the or the tools or the means
to rule any large area.
So for the longest time you had kingdoms
and empire that were isolated and and
localized and they never really came
into contact with each other. Past
10,000 years we're going back to the
birth of agriculture essentially. So uh
but if you want to ask me about the
three largest empires I would say in
third place would come the Mongol Empire
which was founded by Shri Chingis Khan.
It went to the greatest extent its
greatest geographical extent under his
sons and grandsons. the Mongol Empire.
Uh if you want if why don't we take a
look at u
uh what its extent would have been like.
Mongol Empire
uh yeah the largest extent
geographically. So here's what it looked
like. Okay, this was the largest
geographical extent of the Mongol
Empire. Um
about 1368 AD. That's the Mongol Empire
and as you can see they left India out
because they didn't want to invade. Uh
so that's the Mongol Empire. In my
opinion it's the not in my opinion it is
known to be the third largest empire in
history. The second largest empire in
history was the British Empire.
The British Empire and and this is
actually underplaying it. They they
actually uh controlled probably more
than this. But yeah sure this is the
British Empire at its greatest extent
more or less and the sun never set on
the British Empire. Now that's the
second largest empire which is the
largest empire of all. It's the US
empire the American empire but it's not
regarded as an empire today because it's
uh yeah so the US empire is the greatest
empire largest empire. It has a power
position capabilities all across the
world. It can intervene militarily at
essentially 60 to 60 minutes notice
anywhere on the surface of the planet.
And it is you know there are two kinds
of empires
uh
two two two methodologies of of of
maintaining an empire. You either do it
through military occupation or do
otherwise you do it through hedgemony.
To maintain an empire through military
occupation you need to put your military
on the ground boots on the ground which
is extremely expensive. A better way is
to have a hegemonic empire in which you
don't actually put boots to the ground,
but you co-opt various local countries,
turn them into vasals, and you have them
do whatever you want. Like the US and
Indonesia, which we discussed earlier.
The US will levy 19% tariffs on
Indonesia, but Indonesia can't apply
tariffs on on American imports, but
that's what you do if you're an empire.
So that's how the US essentially
controls the whole world to a very large
extent. It doesn't control Russia, it
doesn't control China, doesn't control
India very much very much. But overall
it controls a greater portion of the
world than the British Empire did. So
the American Empire which is the current
hegemonic empire superpower that's the
greatest largest empire of all time.
Number two is the British Empire. Number
three was the Mongol Empire and then
there must be many more. I can name many
more if you like but top three these are
the top three.
Okay. Um
Sunmoon says should school start start
teaching civic sense yeah civic sense in
Indians you know thing. Um is it
something you teach in school? Sure you
can teach in school but how do you teach
it? That's the question. In India in in
school they will give you a textbook and
they'll say repeat after me. You must
have civic sense and then you have to
write a 500word essay on civic sense and
they will give you 20 marks for it.
That's how they teach you things.
Everything is theoretical.
You will learn nothing through that
actually. So you can write an essay
every day about civic sense. You will
learn nothing through it. The only way
to actually learn civic sense is to
practice it. So every day before you
know the Japanese, they teach civic
sense to their kids by from the time
they're about 3 four years old. the kids
they they clean up the classroom they
pick up all the all the all the trash
and put it into dust bins they actually
practice it every day and that's how we
learn it and also you have enforcement
so I think that's how schools can teach
civic sense
schools are supposed to teach you
everything practically but Indian
schools don't do that and Indians don't
even realize that everything has to be
taught practically not theoretically if
you make students memorize all kinds of
stuff it will have no effect on their
life they will learn no skill. They will
simply memorize and retain information
for some time until the exam is done.
Then they will forget everything. That's
not how you teach anything at all. The
only way to teach something is by doing
by making students do things. So yeah,
schools should do it but schools in
India don't do that. So
uh one more question.
Suresh says if given the chance to move
to Mars, would you move?
I I don't mind traveling to Mars. But
moving to Mars, I mean permanently, no
thank you. I'm a guy of Earth. Earth is
my home. I would never move to Mars
permanently. There are many people who
say that, you know, if if I'm given the
chance, I don't mind moving to Mars
permanently and dying there. Well, I
don't want that. I would jump at the
opportunity to travel to Mars, visit the
place and return, but moving there, no
thank you. I am not moving there
permanently.
Okay, that brings me to the end of the
questions. So, almost two hours. Very
well chosen. Um, and Bobby as always has
something interesting to say and add.
The Roman Empire was greater, longer in
time scale and had much more influence
compared to um, so Bobby has his own
scale. It looks like it would drop the
Mongol Empire, the top three powerful,
etc. What's your top empire, Bobby?
Um, the Mongols had 100 years bit of
reach. Euro
Roman Empire lasted way longer, had much
more of an impact. Yeah, you can you can
argue this until the the
uh Yeah, until forever essentially.
M1 says, should men get married in
today's day and age? Is it better to
just live single and die childless? The
system is empty, man. Men, kids are
expensive. The juice isn't worth the
squeeze. Excuse me, what?
Uh I think you should you should get
married.
the system. Don't let the system defeat
you. Don't let the system kill you. Find
the right person. Get married.
And yeah, I I am totally pro marriage. I
think that people should get married.
People should get married early before
the before the age of 25. You should
have kids as soon as possible. And lots
of people will disagree with me because
they are geniuses, but whatever. That's
my opinion.
Because if you want to if you do want to
have kids someday and if you wait until
you're 40 years old to have kids, then
you're going to have to
be strong and active and energetic until
at least
you until you're at least 60, right?
Until the kid is 20. And your
responsibility isn't over by the by the
time your kid is 18 or 20.
A person matures by the time they're 40.
Believe me. Okay? You're not mature
until you reach at least 40 years of
age. until the time you need your
parents to take care of you in some way
or the other.
Uh so the best thing is to the best
thing to do is to marry as soon as
possible and have kids as soon as
possible and and be done with it. And
yeah, you are right that the system is
is very anti-man. That's true. I agree
with you. And today the system is such
that having a single kid is super
expensive. Having two is like
prohibitive.
Uh so yeah the system is is is is
constructed architected in such a way
that it it it's terrible to have kids.
It's very difficult to have kids. It's
very expensive to have kids. And that's
why you will see that the birth rates
and total fertility rates are going down
all across the world. They want a
population collapse to happen and it's
happening. Uh but overall I would say
that you know it's very important for
everybody to have kids to to get married
to have a good partner in life because
eventually you're going to end up all
lonely otherwise and it's not good.
Okay. All right. Uh
Amisha says, "How many solar systems are
present in the Milky Way galaxy?" I
think I don't remember. 10 billion. 10
trillion. Not trillion. No,
I think several billion stars. I don't
remember right now. Let's quickly do a
Google search. How many stars in the
Milky Way?
Milky Way, I think it's 10 billion or
so. Okay. 100 to 400 billion stars. Uh
yeah, so that's the number. Okay. And uh
if that's the number and if each star is
a solar system, well then you have it
100 to 400 billion solar systems in the
Milky Way because we know that most
stars have planets. We know that by now.
So
uh geopolitical dub says does China
really think about Ric or it's just a
statement? Look, if you look at that,
people don't change, right? People don't
change. So, if you want to know what
somebody really is like, just look at
their track record past 10, 20 years.
Have has China ever wanted RAC to become
a thing? Have they ever taken it
seriously? They've never taken it
seriously. They've always been the
spoiler. They've always come in the way
of RA becoming a thing of RC becoming a
viable global coalition that can be
geopolitically viable and and impactful.
China has always played the spoiler
spoiler role. Do you think they'll
suddenly change some one fine morning
and now they'll say, you know what,
let's make RA happen. No, they won't.
They won't. China will will always be
the spoiler when it comes to RA. So, I
don't trust the Chinese. Nope. It's just
words, empty words, blah blah blah.
Okay.
Um,
U says, "How are your people from Ubu
Mua?" Well, they're quite far away, so
it takes time to communicate with them.
You know, there's a lag, but they're
doing all right, and they're hoping that
we don't launch a rescue mission because
they would like to return to wherever
they came from.
Okay.
Favorite character from Friends says Jot
Riani.
Uh Friends. I've seen a few of those
episodes. It's pretty fun, harmless
nonsense mostly. Favorite character.
There were five of them, right? Joey was
the funniest of the lot. Joey, how you
doing? And Rachel.
Phoebe was fun. The the smelly cat
singer.
I think either Phoebe or or or or Joey
or who's it who's Rachel, Monica or
Yeah.
Okay, let's maybe take um a couple more
questions.
Um
anything interesting you guys want to
ask me?
Ball Boys says your favorite sitcom?
I've seen a lot. I I like sitcoms that
make me laugh, you know, and I don't
want to know the whole backstory. I just
want to watch an episode and it should
be funny enough. Maybe two and a half
men.
Uh Bobby says, "What about Chandler?"
Thank you for reminding me of Chandler.
Chandler probably. It's Chandler.
Yeah, late
late Chandler who the actor passed away
a few some time ago. Yeah, he he
probably was the best character
probably. Yeah.
Uh, Mleven says, "Bro, forgot about
Chandler." Uh, thank you for reminding
me. Chandler was probably the best
character. I agree.
Okay. Okay.
Park says, "What's up with your personal
life?" Well, this is not a question.
This is not a show about my personal
life, so we will not discuss that here.
Okay. Do we have any interesting
questions?
Uh, Ou says, "Water fast." I mean, look
at me. Do I look like I'm water fasting
right now?
Uh,
Latangi Shures says, "Please increase
the per week shows nowadays per week to
right now only two." Yeah. Geio
strategy. And look, some people will
argue that quality quantity has a
quality of its own. I mean, after all,
Joseph Stalin said that. So when you
talk about quantity having a quality of
its own, you bring that argument into
play. When your quality is low,
okay, when the quality is low, let's
say, let's say we're talking about
tanks, you have tanks, but your tanks
aren't great. Then let's massproduce
10,000 okay tanks. Then even though
they're not great tanks, they'll be
formidable as a force collectively.
Maybe your aircraft are just third
generation fighter planes, but you've
got a thousand of those, well then they
become a threat anyway. So when your
quality isn't great, that's when you can
increase your quantity and quantity
acquires a quality of its own. But when
your quality is high, when I have fifth
generation fighter planes, stealth
fighter planes, why do I need that
quantity?
So let's I I anyway I I take your point.
Maybe once in a while I can have extra
shows. Maybe once in a while if you guys
want I can do a live stream with super
chats per perhaps. I did the experiment
for a while. Well, let's see. Uh Sri
Raandraama says who do you support Tom
or Jerry? I
used to watch Tom and Jerry as a little
kid.
It was an infuriating show. I wanted Tom
to win. I want to see an episode in
which Tom eats Jerry because that's how
that's the the that's the way nature is
supposed to be, right? I would like to
see Tom eat Jerry one of these days. Tom
is a cat. Jerry's a mouse. Come on. And
Jerry wins all the time. Come on. That's
that's it's not fair.
Bookshelf tour.
You know what? I'll do it next week. But
I won't do it standing here with the
bookshelf. I'll take a bunch of books,
put them on a desk, and maybe I'll do
multiple episodes. Maybe 10 books in one
episode, and I I can do a whole series
of them because I've forgot so many
books. I've got a lot of those. You know
what? Next week, I I'll put up one of
these episodes. I'll sit on on my
podcast desk that you've seen and I'll
put up maybe we'll we'll talk about 10
15 books and we can do I don't know many
episodes that way. So, sure.
[Music]
McLevin says, "Can you suggest some
toxic masculinity movies like Rambo, The
Good, The Bad, The Ugly, etc. Predator,
Arnold Schwarzenegger?"
Die Hard. Yeah, Die Hard with a
vengeance.
Um, The Terminator, Kunan the Barbarian,
all toxic masculinity movies. There was
this great phase in the 1980s where you
had these unabashed masculine movies,
action movies, but there was no
lecturing of the audience, no
vocism or or or or what is it?
Liberalism or nonsense. It was just
factual straightforward,
you know, action movies. I am not
somebody who is a huge fan of action
movies, but some of these movies were
great. The Predator was great.
Terminator, Terminator 2 was great. Um,
and like I said, the Die Hard series
were good and so on. So, the good, the
bad, and the ugly is from the 1960s.
It's a spaghetti western. Sergio Leon,
outstanding. It's not a toxic
masculinity movie. It's a very gritty
movie. Uh, and one of the greatest
movies of all time, of course. So, yeah,
that's what I can remember. I'm sure
there are many more, but yeah,
if you ask me who the main actors are,
it's Silver Sister Stone with the Rocky
series and Rambo series. Um, it's Arnold
Schwarzenegger, of course, and the
movies he made and Bruce Willis to some
extent.
Yeah.
Okay.
The Mummy is not a toxic masculinity
movie. It's not that sort of action
movie. It's a kids movie. It's a kids
movie. Are you kidding me? You've got to
watch the 1980s movies. That's the real
stuff.
Uh, Reacher. Reacher. I saw the
I think the first season possibly of
Reacher. It was kind of good. I think
they've ruined I I hear they've ruined
the second season. So,
um,
okay, I'm going to end it over here. So,
thank you so much everybody for all the
questions. It was fun as always and I
look forward to seeing you in the next
live stream which hopefully happens as
soon as I can make it happen. And do let
me know in the comments below if you
would like me to do maybe more more
super chat live streams. I could do
that. I don't mind doing that. One live
stream per week from in which I take
questions from the comments so that the
standards stay up and then one one super
chat live stream in case you want to ask
all kinds of random questions. I'll take
those. Let me know in the comments
below. Thank you so much for watching.
Keep asking questions. Keep raising your
standards. Keep learning and I'll see
you very soon. Thank you. Bye-bye.